Guide to the John Gerassi Collection of Jean-Paul Sartre
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Gerassi collection of Jean-Paul Sartre
1964-1998
GEN MSS 441
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.5
(13 boxes)
The collection consists primarily of audio interviews made by John Gerassi with Jean-Paul Sartre between 1970 and 1974. A companion group of interviews with Sartre's family, friends, and foes was made in 1973. Included in this group are: Raymond Aron, Simone de Beauvoir, Arlette Elkaim-Sartre, Claude Lanzmann, and J. B. Pontalis. The majority of these interviews have transcripts. Among the other papers are various works by Sartre on Ethics, in the form of lecture notes and manuscript drafts prepared in the 1960s as well as a list by Sartre of books he read in different periods of his life. Also included are notes by John Gerassi on the origin of the collection.
Other Storage Formats: Audiotape boxes, Compact Discs
Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 8-13 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Use copies of audiotapes have been created for consultation. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies (on compact disc) of audiotapes available.
JEAN-PAUL SARTRE (1905-1980)
The life of Jean-Paul Sartre, French novelist and Existentialist philosopher, has been recounted in numerous books. Of particular relevance to this collection is John Gerassi's own biographical study, Jean-Paul Sartre: Hated Conscience of his Century (1989; University of Chicago Press).
Scope and Contents
The John Gerassi Collection of Jean-Paul Sartre consists of manuscripts by Sartre, and interviews with Sartre and his contemporaries. Gathered by John Gerassi during the preparation of his biography Jean-Paul Sartre: Hated Conscience of his Century (1989; University of Chicago Press), the collection spans the years 1964-1985,
As detailed in Gerassi's biography, Sartre was a close friend of Gerassi's parents, Fernando and Stepha. As an adult, Gerassi's friendship with Sartre continued. Sartre eventually asked Gerassi to write his biography and agreed to a series of interviews recorded between 1970-1974. A companion series of interviews with Sartre's friends, contemporaries, and enemies was made in 1973. These interviews comprise Series I. Interviews, which consists of transcripts. The original audiotapes, along with duplicates made on Ampex reel-to-reel tape, are stored with Restricted Materials. In a few cases where a transcript was not received, the original recording is cited. Specific omissions include:
No transcript received for: Sartre interview #3, Part I; "Sartre interview for Ramparts", 1971 Apr 22; Simone de Beauvoir interviews, 1973 May 14 and Nov 15; Troupe Matthews interview, 1985 May 2
No original tape received for: Francis Jeanson interview, 1973 Nov 13-14; Claude Morgan interview, 1973 Jun 6; David Rousset interview, 1973 Mar 14
No Sartre interview #7 exists, due to an original miscount.
Audio duplicates have been made for all of the interviews. [They will be made available on audio CDs for consultation in the Beinecke Library.]
Series II, Other Papers, includes notes and drafts prepared by Sartre for a series of lectures prepared for the Gramsci Insitute in Rome in 1964. These notes were typed by Arlette Elkaim. Sartre then reworked these notes into a book-length manuscript, which was typed by the publishing house Gallimard in 1964. This typescript original, uncorrected, was later returned to Sartre, who gave it to John Gerassi.
The collection also includes notes on ethics, stretching to 800 manuscript pages, prepared for a course proposed for Cornell University in 1965. These notes are unpaginated and have been kept in the order in which they were received in 5 folders according to placement in original binders. Sartre did not come to Cornell in protest of the US bombing of North Vietnam. Sartre later gave these materials to Gerassi.
Series II also contains "Sartre's reading in Youth", an annotated list by Sartre of books he read at specific periods of his life. This list was made by Sartre at Gerassi's request.
This series concludes with notes from Gerassi about the origin and content of the collection, as well as the original folders in which the material was received.
Authors, French -- 20th Century; Philosophers -- France; Interviews; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Aron, Raymond, 1905-1983 -- Interviews; Beauvoir, Simone de, 1908-1986 -- Interviews; Elkaïm-Sartre, Arlette -- Interviews; Gerassi, John; Lanzmann, Claude, 1925- -- Interviews; Pontalis, J.-B., 1924-2013 -- Interviews; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980 -- Interviews; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980 -- Friends and associates; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980
- Interviews, 1970-85; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I., Interviews is organized into three subseries: John Gerassi Interviews with Jean-Paul Sartre (arranged chronologically); Other Sartre Interviews (arranged chronologically); and John Gerassi Interviews with Family, Friends, & Foes of Sartre (arranged alphabetically). This series contains original transcripts made from audiotapes. It has been noted where transcripts are lacking or original tapes do not exist. Original audiotapes are restricted. Audio use copies have been made for reference. These are listed in Appendix A.
  - JOHN GERASSI INTERVIEWS WITH JEAN-PAUL SARTRE
    - Interview 1, 1970 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Interview 2, 1970 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Interview 3, 1970 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Related Materials
      [Part II only. Transcript of part I not received, see audiotapes]
    - Interview 4, 1970 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Interview 5, 1971 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Interview 6, 1971 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Interview 7
    - Interview 8, 1971 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Interview 9, 1971 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Interview 10, 1971 Apr 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Interview 11, 1971 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Interview 12, 1971 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Interview 13, 1971 Jun 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Interview 14, 1971 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Interview 15, 1971 Oct 29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Interview 16, 1971 Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Interview 17, 1971 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Interview 18, 1971 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Interview 19, 1971 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Interview 20, 1972 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Interview 21, 1972 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Interview 22, 1972 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Interview 23, 1972 Mar 24 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Interview 24, 1972 Apr 21 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Interview 25, 1972 May 5 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Interview 26, 1972 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Interview 27, 1972 Jun 2 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Interview 28, 1972 Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Interview 29, 1972 Oct 13 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Interview 30, 1972 Oct 27 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Interview 31, 1972 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Interview 32, 1973 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Interview 33, 1973 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Interview 34, 1973 Jun 28 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Interview 35, 1973 Nov 14 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - OTHER SARTRE INTERVIEWS
    - "Sartre interview for Ramparts", 1971 Apr 22
      [No transcript received, see audiotapes]
    - "Sartre (Speciale)", 1974 Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - JOHN GERASSI INTERVIEWS WITH FAMILY, FRIENDS, & FOES OF SARTRE
    - Aron, Raymond, 1973 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Audry, Colette, 1973 Mar 14 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Beauvoir, Simone de, 1973 Jan 30 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      [No transcript received for 1973 May 14 or Nov 15 interviews, see audiotapes]
    - Bloch, Pierre, 1973 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Burnier, Michel-Antoine, 1972 Nov 12 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Contat, Michel, 1973 Mai 28 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Elkaim-Sartre, Arlette, 1973 Mar 5 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Gorz, André, 1973 Jun 10 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      Biographical / Historical
      [also known as: Michel Bosquet and Gérard Horz]
      [includes note dated 1973 Mar 29]
    - Jeanson, Francis, 1973 Nov 13-14 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      Existence and Location of Originals
      [Original tape not received]
    - Kozakievitch, Wanda, 1973 Mar 23 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Kozakievitch-Bost, Olga, 1973 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      [also known as: Olga Dominique]
    - Lanzmann, Claude, 1973 Jun 5 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Léglise-Vian, Michèle, 1973 Mar 7 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Leroy, Henri, 1973 Jun 26 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Maheu, René, 1973 May 22 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Matthews, Troupe, 1985 May 2
    - Morgan, Claude, 1973 Jun 6 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Pontalis, J. B., 1973 Mar 20 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Pouillon, Jean, 1973 Mar 16 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Rousset, David, 1973 Mar 14 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Other Papers, 1964-98, n.d.; Series II; 1.65; (4 boxes)
  Series II., Other Papers is divided into two subseries: Writings of Jean-Paul Sartre; and Original Collection Material.
  - WRITINGS OF JEAN-PAUL SARTRE
    - Notes for lecture on ethics prepared for Gramsci Institute, typescript, corrected, [1964] (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Manuscript on ethics prepared by Gallimard, typescript, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 56-57)
    - Manuscript on ethics prepared by Gallimard, typescript, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Notes for lecture on ethics prepared for Cornell University, holograph, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 59-60)
    - Notes for lecture on ethics prepared for Cornell University, holograph, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 61-63)
    - List of books: "Sartre's reading in Youth", holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - ORIGINAL COLLECTION MATERIAL
    - Notes by John Gerassi on origin of collection, ca. 1998 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Original manuscript covers received with collection, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 66)
- Restricted Fragile Materials
  Restricted Fragile Materials contains original audiotapes.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Use copies of audiotapes have been created for consultation. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - JOHN GERASSI INTERVIEWS WITH JEAN-PAUL SARTRE
    - 41 audio cassette tapes (Box 8–10)
  - OTHER SARTRE INTERVIEWS
    - 3 audio cassette tapes (Box 10)
  - JOHN GERASSI INTERVIEWS WITH FAMILY, FRIENDS, & FOES OF SARTRE
    - 22 audio cassette tapes (Box 11)
  - DUPLICATES OF INTERVIEWS
    - 10 Master AMPEX audiotapes (Box 12–13)